A Guide to the Henry Thweatt Owen Papers, 1822-1929
Library of Virginia
Library of Virginia
Henry Thweatt Owen Papers, 1822-1929
Library of Virginia
28154
0.45 cubic feet.
Emerson G. Whiteside lent this collection for copying over a period of years. These photocopies were filed as Accessions 21918, 22000, and 26092. The original material was gradually given to the library (Accessions 26091, 27683, 27774, and 28154). With the receipt of Accession 28154, the photocopies was given to the Virginia Historical Society. The various accessions comprising the Henry Thweatt Owen Papers (Accessions 26091, 27683, 27774, and 28154) are interfiled with Accession 28154. Also interfiled are the Owen Papers (Accession 23838) given to the Library by Constance Watson.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
There are no restrictions.
Acquisition Information
Gifts of Constance Watson and Emerson G. Whitside, Richmond, Virginia, July 1952-December 1973.
Biographical/Historical Information
Born 28 July 1831, Henry Thweatt Owen entered the Confederate Army as a Captain of Company C, 18th Virginia Infantry Regiment on 23 April 1861 in Burkeville, Virginia. He was arrested on 5 June 1861, but by order of court martial was restored to command on 1 July 1861. He was again placed under arrest, this time for disobeying orders in regard to some sick men in his company, on 11 September 1861, by order of Colonel R. E. Withers, his commanding officer, and was cashiered on 22 November 1861. However, his order of cashier was vacated, and he was elected Captain by his company on 26 April 1862. He was reported absent from the lines in Chesterfield County, Virginia, on 28 December 1864, by reason of his being under arrest and imprisoned in Castle Thunder. The reasons for Owen's frequent arrests remain a mystery, except for the arrest of 11 September 1861, and even in this case the matter is only partially explained in a letter of 29 March 1902 from Owen to Colonel R. E. Withers. Owen's war letters mention his arrests, but give no reasons.
Following the war, he served as a clerk in the Second Auditor's Office in Richmond and devoted his spare time to investigating the Land Office records for genealogical information, and compiled preliminary maps showing plats of land grants in Prince Edward County. His wife was named Harriet, who bore him twelve children: Elizabeth Mildred (1852-1867), Henry Clay (1853-1883), Michael Melancthon (1856-1949), Harriet Louisa (b. 1860), Jacqueline Rosa (b. 1865), William Temple (1867-1879), Herman S. (b. 1868), Benjamin Hilton (1868-1896), Sallie Marshall (b. 1871), Helen Mercer (b. 1873), Mary Eliza (Mamie) (b. 1875), and Charles Archer (1877-1879). Owen died in Richmond on 8 October 1921.
Scope and Content Information
Papers, 1822-1929, including a will (29 April 1822) and estate inventory (28 November 1825) of Ann Owen of Prince Edward County, letters, land records, military papers, lists of casualties and units at Gettysburg, a diary kept during the Civil War from 10 February to 10 July 1863, reminiscences of service during the Civil War, drafts of articles concerning the Civil War, poetry, a newspaper (Charlottesville Gazette, 15 May 1884), photographs of Henry Thweatt Owen, the papers of James Whiteside, maps, broadsides, and lists of coupons issued under Acts of 1871, 1879, and 1892 and paid into the Second Auditor's Office.
The letters, 1856-1924, comprise the bulk of the collection and concern Owen's military service, his desire for historical accuracy regarding the role of Pickett's Division in the Gettysburg campaign, postwar Virginia politics, and his career in the Second Auditor's Office. Correspondents includes James Lawson Kemper, James Longstreet, Philip W. McKinney, William Mahone, Charles Marshall, Roger A. Pryor, and Frank G. Ruffin.
The military papers, 6 November 1862 - 8 August 1864, include letters, orders, and receipts of a military nature, especially concerning Union prisoners assembled for exchange at City Point. Lists of casualties and units at Gettysburg, n.d., include estimates of Union strength, company rosters, and lists of officers killed and wounded in Pickett's Charge. Diary, 10 February - 10 July 1863, traces the movements of the 18th Virginia Infantry Regiment from Petersburg through the retreat from Gettysburg.
Reminiscences are of Owen's service during the Civil War, Pickett's division, the Battle of South Mountain, and Pickett's Charge. James Whiteside papers, 1863-1893, include a discharge from the 46th Pennsylvania Militia Regiment, survey and plat of land in Charlotte County, receipts, and accounts.
The maps include a railroad map of the United States with an emphasis on distances between San Francisco and Richmond (before 1889); a plat of Old Point Comfort (1891); plats, surveys, and notes concerning early settlers in Prince Edward County (ca. 1728 - ca. 1783, n.d.); plats and maps of property in and near the town of Virso, Prince Edward and Lunenburg Counties (ca. 1920 - ca. 1924); and a map of the first day of the Battle of Gettysburg (1876). These maps are located in Map cabinet 22, drawer 1. The broadsides consist of: "To the Survivors of Pickett's Division," 15 December 1887, and "Garnett's Brigade," n.d. The lists of coupons issued under Acts of 1871, 1879, 1892 and paid into the Second Auditor's Office are printed forms, filled in. The broadside and lists of coupon are located in Map cabinet 22, drawer 1.
Organization
Organized into the following sixteen series: I. Ann Owen Papers, 1822, 1825. II. Letters, 1856-1924. III. Land Records, 1894-1928. IV. Military Papers, 1862-1864. V. Lists of Casualties and Units at Gettysburg. VI. Diary, 10 February-10 July 1863. VII. Reminiscences. VIII. Draft of Articles. IX. Poetry. X. Newspaper. XI. Photographs. XII. James Whiteside Papers, 1863-1893. XIII. Plat Books. XIV. Maps. XV. Broadsides. XVI. Second Auditor's Office.
Contents List
- Ann Owen Papers, 1822, 1825
  - Will, 29 April 1822, 8 p.; Of Ann Owen, Prince Edward County, Virginia. Proved 21 November 1825. (Folder 1)
  - Inventory and appraisement of estate, 28 November 1825, 7 p.; Of Ann Owen, Prince Edward County, Virginia. (Folder 1)
- Letters, 1856-1924
  - 5 July 1856, 3 p.; Henry T. Owen, Blacksburg, Virginia, to his wife [Harriet Owen], concerning his trip, the view from Peaks of Otter, and the quality of the land and crops in the area. (Folder 2)
  - 28 August 1861, 4 p.; Henry T. Owen, "Camp near Centreville" [Fairfax County], Virginia, to his wife [Harriet Owen], on his own recent illness, the myth of rampant sickness in the army, his objections to married men in service, financial matters, and education. (Folder 2)
  - 9 October 1861, 2 p.; Henry T. Owen, Fairfax Court House, Virginia, to his wife [Harriet Owen], sending a bag of chestnuts, discussing financial affairs, commenting on the possibilities of a battle, and mentioning that his case (not described) has not yet been brought before a court martial. (Folder 2)
  - 7-8 November 1861, 4 p.; Henry T. Owen, Centreville, Virginia, to his wife [Harriet Owen], concerning family financial affairs, and describing the departure of his former lawyer and the postponement of his trial. (Folder 2)
  - 12 March 1862, 2 p.; Henry T. Owen, Camp Wise, Richmond, Virginia, to Harriet Owen, reporting rumors of retreat from Manassas. (Folder 2)
  - 14 March 1864, 2 p.; Henry T. Owen, Camp Wise, Richmond, Virginia, to Harriet Owen [Nottoway County, Virginia], reporting on life in camp and asking her to assist the men getting more recruits for his company. (Folder 2)
  - 18 March 1862, 2 p.; Henry T. Owen, Gordonsville, Virginia, to Harriet Owen [Nottoway County, Virginia], describing move to Gordonsville from Richmond and rumors of his regiment's retreat toward Richmond. (Folder 2)
  - 10 April 1862, 2 p.; Henry T. Owen, Louisa County, Virginia, to Harriet Owen [Nottoway County, Virginia], concerning the army's marches and counter marches between Louisa Court House and Fredericksburg, and Harriet Owen's health. (Folder 2)
  - Letter, 11 April 1862, 2 p.; Henry T. Owen, Louisa Court House, Virginia, to Harriet Owen [Nottoway County, Virginia], regarding the army's proposed march to Richmond, and suggesting means by which she could travel there to see him. (Folder 2)
  - Letter, 20 April 1862, 4 p.; Henry T. Owen, "Camp near Yortown," Virginia, to Harriet Owen [Nottoway County, Virginia], bemoaning the lack of mail and the fact that they were unable to meet in Richmond, and describing life in the woods. (Folder 2)
  - 24 April 1862, 2 p.; Henry T. Owen, "Camp near Yorktown," Virginia, to Harriet Owen [Nottoway County, Virginia], on their children and her health. (Folder 2)
  - 27 April 1862, 2 p.; Henry T. Owen, "Camp near Yorktown," Virginia, to Harriet Owen {Nottoway County, Virginia], reporting his election as captain of the company. (Folder 2)
  - 6 May 1862, 4 p.; Henry T. Owen, "On march from Williamsburg," Virginia, to Harriet Owen [Nottoway County, Virginia], describing his first battle as captain and listing the dead and wounded. (Folder 2)
  - 11 May 1862, 2 p.; Henry T. Owen, [Chickahominy River] Virginia, to Harriet Owen [Nottoway County, Virginia], describing the recovery of some of the soldiers wounded in the recent battle, and on family matters. (Folder 2)
  - 21 May 1862, 4 p.; Henry T. Owen, "Laurel Hill Church below Richmond," to Harriet Owen [Nottoway County, Virginia], concerning her proposed move to Prince Edward County and the weak patriotism of some of her neighbors, providing further news on the recovery of the wounded, and commenting on her news. (Folder 2)
  - 1 June 1862, 2 p.; Henry T. Owen, "York River Rail Road 6 miles Below Richmond," Virginia, to his wife [Harriet Owen], describing the battle he was in that day, listing the killed and wounded, and reassuring her that he was safe. (Folder 2)
  - 12 June 1862, 2 p.; Henry T. Owen, "Camp near Richmond," Virginia, to Harriet Owen, giving war news and encouraging her to send their son Clay to visit him in camp. (Folder 2)
  - 16 June 1862, 4 p.; Henry T. Owen, "Wmsbg Road Below Richmond," Virginia, to Harriet Owen, describing an opportunity for a visit home which duty compelled him to pass up in favor of one of his Lieutenants, and his sadness over the depleted ranks of his company. (Folder 2)
  - 21 June 1862, 2 p.; Henry T. Owen to his wife [Harriet Owen], relating a story of the capture and punishment of a deserter. (Folder 2)
  - 28 June 1862, 2 p.; Henry T. Owen to his wife [Harriet Owen], listing wounded in "battles of the last two days"; he himself had been ill and stayed in camp. (Folder 2)
  - 30 June 1862, 2 p.; Henry T. Owen, "On Wmsburg Road," Virginia, to Harriet Owen, discussing his recovery and the battles of the past few days, and expressing the hope that McClellan will soon be surrounded and forced to surrender (Folder 2)
  - 16 July 1862, 4 p.; Henry T. Owen, "Camp below Richmond, Darby Town Road," to Harriet Owen, on the subject of his farm and crops, and a deserter. (Folder 2)
  - 27 July 1862, 2 p.; Henry T. Owen, "In Camp [Richmond, Virginia]," to Harriet Owen, sending her some of his clothing and blankets, and some newspapers, and discussing family matters. (Folder 2)
  - 31 August 1862, 2 p.; Henry T. Owen, "Manassas Plains [Prince William County, Virginia]," to Harriet Owen, describing Second Battle of Manassas and listing the killed and wounded in his regiment. (Folder 2)
  - 7 November 1862, 4 p., fragment.; Henry T. Owen, "Camp near Culpeper Court House," Virginia, to Harriet Owen, describing his snug lean-to, the cold, snowy weather, and waxing literary on "the far off, dull, sullen muttering of the deep mouthed cannon." (Folder 2)
  - 14 December 1862, 2 p.; Henry T. Owen, "Camp near Fredericksburg," Virginia, to Harriet Owen, on the battles around Fredericksburg in which his unit has not been engaged. (Folder 2)
  - 14 March 1863, 4 p.; Henry T. Owen, "Pitt Co., N.C.," to Harriet Owen, describing the march through North Carolina, a swamp near the camp, and his brigade's regret at being detached temporarily from General Pickett's command. (Folder 2)
  - 6 April 1863, 4 p.; Henry T. Owen, "Camp before Washington, N.C.," to his daughter, "Miss E. Millie Owen," asking for a letter from her, describing his hardships, and telling the story of a little boy who had never seen hardtack before. (Folder 2)
  - 13 June 1863, 2 p.; Henry T. Owen, Culpeper Court House, Virginia, to his wife [Harriet Owen], speculating about where the army might go, recommending study and discipline for his children, and hoping his son might come to visit him. (Folder 2)
  - 16 June 1863, 2 p.; Henry T. Owen, Rappahannock Co., Virginia, to Harriet Owen, regarding the uncertainty of their destination or route of march, and his religious conversion to Presbyterianism. (Folder 2)
  - 21 June 1863, 4 p.; Henry T. Owen, "Bivouac near Berryville, Clarke Co., Va.," to Harriet Owen, describing their march by the Shenandoah River, mentioning people they both know, speculating on his chances for promotion now that the sentence of cashier (no reason given) has been removed by the Secretary of War, and discussing religion and family matters. (Folder 2)
  - 18 July 1863, 2 p.; Henry T. Owen, Bunker Hill, Berkeley County, Virginia, to Harriet Owen, concerning the prisoners taken by his unit at Gettysburg and telling a long story about one of them, Captain Frank R. Josselyn of Massachusetts. (Folder 2)
  - 22 July 1863, 2 p.; Henry T. Owen, "Near Front Royale," Virginia, to Harriet Owen, about his leading the remaining sixty-three men of his regiment against enemy cavalry at Chester Gap, and news of friends. (Folder 2)
  - 24 July 1863, 2 p.; Henry T. Owen, Culpeper Court House, Virginia, to Harriet Owen, concerning his sadness at so many of his men and comrades no longer being with him, and giving news of some local soldiers. (Folder 2)
  - 7 September 1863, 2 p.; Henry T. Owen, Orange County, Virginia, to his son, Henry Clay Owen, on family friends and matters. (Folder 2)
  - 27 September 1863, 2 p.; Henry T. Owen, Petersburg, Virginia, to his wife [Harriet Owen], regarding his possible posting to City Point and his desire to have his sons Michael and Clay sent to join him in camp. (Folder 2)
  - 21 December 1863, 8 p.; Henry T. Owen, Richmond, Virginia, to his wife [Harriet Owen], giving a long pious discourse on God's blessings on them after his wife had lost her trunk and its contents. (Folder 2)
  - 8 February 1864, 4 p.; Henry T. Owen, Richmond, Virginia, to Harriet Owen, on family matters and friends. (Folder 2)
  - 18 April 1864, 4 p.; Henry T. Owen, Richmond, Virginia, to his son [Henry Clay Owen], on his studies and family matters. (Folder 2)
  - 16 May 1864, 4 p.; Henry T. Owen, Richmond, Virginia, to his wife [Harriet Owen], describing enemy movements in Powhatan and Amelia Counties, and the battles between Richmond and Petersburg. (Folder 2)
  - 20 May 1864, 4 p.; Henry T. Owen, Richmond, Virginia, to Harriet Owen, concerning the mail and the battle near Richmond. (Folder 2)
  - 28 July 1864, 4 p.; W. H. H. Ewing to "Dear Uncle," Henry T. Owen, Moore's Ordinary, Virginia, with war news and family talk. (Folder 2)
  - 22 August 1864, 2 p.; Henry T. Owen, Chester Station, Virginia, to his wife [Harriet Owen], concerning family financial matters, war news, and the health of soldiers from home. (Folder 2)
  - 1 October 1864, 2 p.; Henry T. Owen, Chester Station, Virginia, to his wife [Harriet Owen], regarding soldiers from home, fighting near Richmond, and his feeling that Grant would probably capture Richmond and Petersburg within a month. (Folder 2)
  - 9 October 1864, 4 p.; Henry T. Owen, "Trenches near Chester, Va.," to his wife [Harriet Owen], concerning his brother's possible death or capture, and some war news. (Folder 2)
  - 3 November 1864, 4 p.; Henry T. Owen, "Near Chester Station, Va.," to his wife [Harriet Owen], regarding food sent from home, his relief over hearing his brother was safe, and family matters. (Folder 2)
  - 22 November 1864, 2 p.; Henry T. Owen, Castle Thunder [Richmond, Virginia], to his wife [Harriet Owen], concerning his imprisonment (charges not mentioned). (Folder 2)
  - 1 December 1864, 2 p.; Henry T. Owen, Castle Thunder [Richmond, Virginia], to his wife [Harriet Owen], requesting food, clothing, and books, and speculating on his trial date. (Folder 2)
  - [Saturday morning, 1864], 1 p.; Henry T. Owen to his wife [Harriet Owen], saying that he is sick and will meet her and her father at the depot on Monday. (Folder 2)
  - [1864], 2 p.; Henry T. Owen to his wife [Harriet Owen], concerning money, crops, and war news. (Folder 2)
  - 10 September 1869, 1 p.; Henry T. Owen, appointment as Commissioner in Chancery for the Circuit Court of Prince Edward County, Virginia. (Folder 3)
  - 16 May 1876, 1 p.; Roger A. Pryor, New York, New York, to Colonel Henry T. Owen, informing him that he is returning Owen's manuscript, and regrets that he could not find a publisher. (Folder 3)
  - 27 January 1878, 2 p., fragment.; [Henry T. Owen], Green Bay P. O., Prince Edward County, Virginia, to Colonel Charles Marshall, Baltimore, Maryland, taking issue with Longstreet's recently published letter concerning Lee's actions after Pickett's Charge at Gettysburg, and relating his encounter with Marshall after the charge. (Folder 3)
  - 28 January 1878, 6 p.; Charles Marshall, Baltimore, Maryland, to Captain H. S. Owen [sic], Green Bay [Prince Edward County, Virginia], concerning Lee's actions and statements after Pickett's Charge, and the orders directing Pickett to move his troops from Chambersburg to Gettysburg. (Folder 3)
  - 1 February 1878, 2 p.; J. L. Kemper, Madison, Virginia, to Captain Henry T. Owen, stating that he did not know what orders passed between Longstreet and Pickett regarding the latter's march from Chambersburg to Gettysburg. (Folder 3)
  - 15 February 1878, 1 p.; William Smith, Warrenton, Virginia, to Henry T. Owen, regretting he could not locate the wherabouts of Leonidas Smith, and mentioning a service he did for Owen but had forgotten about. (Folder 3)
  - 23 February 1878, 1 p.; Charles Pickett, Norfolk, Virginia, to Captain Henry T. Owen, estimating the size of Major General George E. Pickett's command at Gettysburg at 4,800 men. (Folder 3)
  - 4 March 1878, 1 p.; J. L. Kemper, Madison, Virginia, to Captain Henry T. Owen, regarding the position of Pickett's dividion and Kemper's brigade. (Folder 3)
  - 15 March 1878, 2 p.; Z. A Blanton, Farmville, Virginia, to Captain Henry T. Owen, responding to questions regarding the units under Pickett's command at Gettysburg. (Folder 3)
  - 24 March 1878, 6 p.; James Longstreet, Gainsville [sic], Georgia, to Captain Henry T. Owen, Green Bay [Prince Edward County], Virginia, concerning the aftermath of the Battle of Gettysburg, Lee's words and actions, the literature on the battle, and Owen's planned writings on the subject. (Folder 3)
  - 28 March 1878, 2 p.; Z. A. Blanton, Farmville, Virginia, to Captain Henry T. Owen, concerning Blanton's part in the Battle of Gettysburg and Pickett's charge. (Folder 3)
  - 30 March 1878, 3 p.; Charles Pickett, Norfolk, Virginia, to Captain Henry T. Owen, Green Bay {Prince Edward County], Virginia, concerning the march of Major General George E. Pickett's troops to Gettysburg and their position prior to the charge of 3 July 1863. (Folder 3)
  - 7 April 1878, 2 p.; George C. Cabell, House of Representatives, Washington, D. C., to Captain Henry T. Owen, regarding the activities of his unit around Manassas Gap, Virginia, after the Battle of Gettysburg. (Folder 3)
  - 8 April 1878, 4 p.; W. J. Morrissett, Bristol, Tennessee, to Captain Henry T. Owen, stating that he has tried to forget the war and look to the future, but attempting to describe the march of Pickett's troops to Gettysburg. (Folder 3)
  - 8 April 1878, 2 p.; John S. Hayes, Afton [Nelson County], Virginia, to Captain Henry T. Owen, Green Bay [Prince Edward County], Virginia, concerning Hayes' recent illness and loss of sight in one eye, his closeness to General Lee during the Gettysburg campaign, and the activities of Pickett's division at Gettysburg. (Folder 3)
  - 14 April 1878, 2 p.; James A. Holland, Glade Hill, Franklin County, Virginia, to Captain Henry T. Owen, regarding the extra duties of Pickett's division while in Chambersburg, their arrival at Gettysburg, and estimates of the losses suffered in Pickett's Charge. (Folder 3)
  - 15 April 1878, 5 p.; John S. Hayes, Afton [Nelson County], Virginia, to Captain Henry T. Owen, Green Bay [Prince Edward County], Virginia, giving detailed accounts of conversations between Generals Lee and Longstreet during the first day of the Battle of Gettysburg, and expressing interest in looking at any manuscript Owen may have written about the war. (Folder 3)
  - 15 April 1878, 2 p.; Roger A. Pryor, New York, New York, to Colonel [Henry T.] Owen, reporting that Owen's manuscript had been received by him, and expressing little hope that it could be published. (Folder 3)
  - 21 April 1878, 1 p.; James Longstreet, Gainesville, Georgia, to Major Henry T. Owen, Virginia, concerning the debate over Pickett's time of arrival at Gettysburg from Chambersburg. (Folder 3)
  - 5 May 1878, 1 p.; James Longstreet, Gainesville, Georgia, to [Henry T. Owen], thanking him for his letter and admitting that both Lee and himself were mistaken as to the time of Pickett's arrival at Gettysburg. (Folder 3)
  - 9 July 1878, 1 p.; Edmund R. Cocke, Oakland, Virginia, to Captain Henry T. Owen, Green Bay [Prince Edward County], Virginia, in regard to Pickett's time of arrival at Gettysburg from Chambersburg. (Folder 3)
  - 18 August 1878, 4 p.; Edward R. Baird, Occupacia, Essex County, Virginia, to Captain Henry T. Owen, concerning the Pickett controversy, stating that Pickett had reported personally to Longstreet, who had then ordered the division into camp for the night. (Folder 3)
  - 6 September 1878, 2 p.; James Longstreet, Gainesville, Georgia, to Major Henry T. Owen, Green Bay [Prince Edward County], Virginia, concerning Pickett's arrival at Gettysburg and the conversations between himself and Lee as reported by Hayes (see the letter of 15 April 1878 above). (Folder 3)
  - 11 November 1878, 5 p.; [Henry T. Owen], Green Bay, Prince Edward County, Virginia, to Richard Irby, correcting errors in Irby's bok, particularly an account of part of the First Battle of Manassas. (Folder 3)
  - 25 November 1878, 2 p.; Richard Irby, Ashland [Hanover County], Virginia, to Captain Henry T. Owen, Meherrin, Virginia, stating that his errors were unintentional and that he would be glad to give credit where it is due in an expanded version of his book. (Folder 3)
  - 11 December 1878, 2 p.; Abner Anderson, Danville, Virginia, to Captain Henry T. Owen, agreeing with his version of the events at Manassas and Yorktown, as opposed to that published by Irby. (Folder 3)
  - 14 December 1878, 2 p; Affidavit by E. B. Coleman, in handwriting of Henry T. Owen, agreeing with Owen's version of the affair at First Manassas when the Federal cannon were turned against them by Owen and others. (Folder 3)
  - 21 December 1878, 2 p.; James A. Holland, "Franklin Co. near Glade Hill," Virginia, to Captain [Henry T. Owen], agreeing with Owen's accounts of First Manassas and Gettysburg. (Folder 3)
  - 30 December 1878, 2 p.; William Mahone, Petersburg, Virginia, to [H. H. Dyson], Richmond, Virginia, offering suggestions as to how to proceed with purging the old staff and making new appointments when Dyson assumes the office of Second Auditor, and commenting on the political scene. Includes envelope. (Folder 3)
  - 30 April 1880, 1 p.; James L, Kemper, Madison, Virginia, to Captain Henry T. Owen, giving an account of his service in the Mexican War. (Folder 3)